James Fred McKale papers, 1891-1967 (bulk 1940-1967)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
James Fred McKale papers, 1891-1967 (bulk 1940-1967)
AZ 284
McKale, James Fred, 1887-1967
This collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, speeches, athletic records, and personal items, concerning University of Arizona athletics. Teams include basketball, baseball, and football. Also included is material relating to his participation in the National Collegiate Athletic Association, the Border Intercollegiate Athletic Conference, and the American Association of College Baseball Coaches.
15 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
James Fred McKale first moved to Tucson, Arizona in 1911 and served as a baseball coach for Tucson High School. Based on his outstanding record students from the University of Arizona petitioned University President A. H. Wilde to hire McKale as the coach for all athletic teams at the U of A. James F. McKale served as Coach and Director of Athletics at the University of Arizona from 1914-1959.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Correspondence and Personal Material, 1903-1967
Series II: Speeches, Printed Materials and Photographs, 1893-1967
Series III: University Athletics and Sports Records, 1891-1967
Series IV: Associations, 1931-1967
Series V: Supplemental Materials, 1899-1967
Series VI: Scrapbooks, 1914-1967
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, speeches, athletic records, and personal items, concerning University of Arizona athletics. Teams include basketball, baseball, and football. Also included is material relating to his participation in the National Collegiate Athletic Association, the Border Intercollegiate Athletic Conference, and the American Association of College Baseball Coaches.
McKale, James Fred, 1887-1967 -- Archives; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Border Intercollegiate Athletic Conference; American Association of College Baseball Coaches; University of Arizona -- Sports -- History; University of Arizona -- Faculty; University of Arizona -- Homecoming; University of Arizona -- Records and correspondence; University of Arizona -- University week; University of Arizona. Dept. of Health, Physical Education and Recreation; University of Arizona -- Buildings; University of Arizona. Student Union; Athletics -- Arizona -- History; Baseball -- Arizona -- History; Football -- Arizona -- History; College sports -- Arizona -- History; Correspondence; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Separated Material
Miscellaneous photographs were integrated into Special Collections' University Photograph files. Eleven large framed photographs are hanging in the McKale Memorial Room, McKale Center.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence and Personal Material, 1903-1967
  - Correspondence, 1928-1967
    - Correspondence: General and miscellaneous. 1940-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence: Homecoming. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Retirement. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Newsletters from Robert Clark. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Paul J. Fannin. 1950-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Barry Goldwater. 1957, 1959, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Bill Henry. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Mrs. Chris Lauesen. 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: F. N. "Pat" Nathan. 1941-1943, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Lyman P. Robertson. 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: B. L. Stanley. 1928, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes a letter from Knute Rockne, University of Notre Dame.
    - Memorial Service and later tributes. June 4, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence returned to library after James F. McKale's death. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Material, 1903-1967
    - Personal miscellany. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes membership cards, poems and resolutions in honor of James F. McKale's "Liar's Medal", first World Series attended, and first airplane ride.
    - The Big "I", personal clippings. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Insurance. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Helms Hall College Baseball Hall of Fame. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Course in Physical and Bayonet Training, Princeton University. November 1918 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - McKale Stadium. 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - McKale Scholarship Fund. 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Retirement. 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 80th Birthday celebration plans. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letters of sympathy to family. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
    - Albion College: Correspondence, etc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Albion College: "Doctor McKale". 1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sigma Nu Fraternity: Various publications, etc. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Sigma Nu Fraternity: Directory. 1941 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - University of Michigan: Summer school notes. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Old Albion, 1861-1909. 1909 (Box 4)
    - Io Triumphe (Albion College Alumni Directory Issue. January 1962 (Box 4)
    - Albion College Scrapbook. 1903-1912 (Box 5)
      Includes material relating to his prior years and Lansing High School and as a coach at Superior, Wisconsin High School and Tucson High School after graduation.
- Series II: Speeches, Printed Materials and Photographs, 1893-1967
  - Newspaper Columns: "McKale Recalls: Sports Oddities", Arizona Republic. 1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Columns: "McKale's 'Knotty Problems'", Arizona Daily Star; Arizona Republic; and Gazette. 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Columns: "2nd Base Coach". Collegiate Baseball Digest. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Speeches: Lincoln. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Includes also Abraham Lincoln: The Politician by James F. McKale, published by the University of Arizona Alumni Association, 1967?
  - Speeches: George Washington. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Speeches: Men's Night. 1958-1966 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Speeches: Miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Speeches: Miscellaneous notes, etc. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photographs. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Clippings: Education and health. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Clippings: Humor. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Clippings: Lincoln. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clippings: Politics, social problems, etc. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "X Book" (volumes 1-3). (Box 7)
  - Books: El Beisbol en Sonora (1877-1950), by Miguel S. Durazo, Sonora. 1945? (Box 8)
  - Books: A Course in Football for Players and Coaches, by Glenn S. Warner, Carlisle, PA. 1912 (Box 8)
  - Books: A Scientific and Practical Treatise on American Football for Schools and Colleges, by A. Alonzo Stagg and Henry L. Williams, Hartford, Conn. 1893 (Box 8)
  - Books: America's National Game... Baseball, by Albert G. Spalding, New York. 1911 (Box 8)
  - Books: United States 1952 Olympic Book (inscribed). 1952 (Box 8)
  - Books: United States 1956 Olympic Book (inscribed). 1956 (Box 8)
  - Die Olympischen Spiele 1936, Hamburg, (Band 2, inscribed). 1932 (Volume 9)
- Series III: University Athletics and Sports Records, 1891-1967
  - Appointments. 1917-1967 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with University Presidents. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Job applications. 1925, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Varsity athletic war casualties. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Physical Education majors and graduates. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Stadium construction. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Ellinwood Vocabulary Contest. 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Student Union building. 1945 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - William J. Bray. 1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - History: S. J. Mansfeld's correspondence with others. 1906-1965 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - History: Correspondence with various persons regarding athletic history. 1941-1960 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - History: Correspondence with S. J. Mansfeld. 1945-1961 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - History: Holiday "Strike". 1904 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous history. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Varsity Lettermen (separate sports lists and miscellaneous material). (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Varsity Managers. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous material. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bobcats. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "University of Arizona Varsity Lettermen," (notebook). 1897-1964 (Box 11)
  - Lettermen's Club Book of Tributes (collection of bound letters). November 8, 1964 (Box 11)
  - Digest of Articles: Arizona Weekly (notebook). 1891-1900 (Box 12)
  - Digest of Articles: Arizona Daily Citizen (notebook). September 1891-August 1915 (Box 12)
  - Digest of Articles: Arizona Daily Star (notebook). September 1891-September 1914 (Box 12)
  - Digest of Articles: Arizona Daily Star (folder containing variations of the above). 1896-1911 (Box 12)
  - Basketball Records. 1904-1964 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Golf Records. 1949-1964 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Swimming Records. 1923-1964 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Tennis Records. 1901-1964 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Sports Records. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Varsity Captains. 1899-1942 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - History of Intercollegiate Athletics at the University of Arizona by Robert S. Svob. 1897-1961 (Box 13)
    Volume 1 is a Master's Thesis cover 1897-1948, volume 2 is a supplement covering 1949-1961.
  - Baseball Records. 1925 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Baseball Records. 1931-1939 (Box 14, Folder 2-8)
  - Baseball Records. 1940-1943 (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
  - Baseball Records. 1946-1947 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Baseball Records (summary). 1898-1964 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Baseball Reunions. 1956-1963 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Baseball Teaching Notes. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Baseball Records and History. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Track Records. 1897-1964 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Early Track and Field Days. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - "Manuscript... on the 1905 U. of A. Football Team and Its Influence on the Modern Game." 1938-1955 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Football Coaches. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Football Records (summary). (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Football Records and History (miscellaneous material). (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Football Notes. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Visiting Football Teams. 1941-1948 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - John "Button" Salmon. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Football Material. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Tempe: The Matesic Siemering Affair ("NCCA Lie", by James F. McKale). 1951-1952 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Football Clippings. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1899 Team. 1949 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1900 Team. 1950 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1901 Team. 1951 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1902 and 1927 Teams. 1952 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1903 and 1928 Teams. 1953 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1904 and 1929 Teams. 1954 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1905 and 1930 Teams. 1955 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1914, 1915, 1916, and 1931 Teams. 1956 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1917 and 1932 Teams. 1957 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1908 and 1933 Teams. 1958 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1909 and 1934 Teams. 1959 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Homecoming: Reunion of 1910 and 1935 Teams. 1960 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Homecomings. 1961-1963 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Homecomings. 1964-1967 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Ernest L. Barnes report to Fred Inke, Jr. 1950 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Report to Vice President Marvin D. Johnson. 1964 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - High School Questionnaire. 1928 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Track and Field Records. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - University Week. 1912-1965 (Box 18, Folder 5-11)
  - Printed programs. (Box 18)
- Series IV: Associations, 1931-1967
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association, 1947-1967
    - College World Series: Clippings, etc. 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - College World Series: Programs. 1950-1967 (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
    - N. C. A. A.: Sanity Code ("Passell of Lies" by James F. McKale). 1948-1949 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - N. C. A. A.: Correspondence. 1947-1958 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - N. C. A. A.: Baseball Questionnaire. 1951-1954 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - N. C. A. A.: Meetings and minutes. 1959-1964 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - N. C. A. A.: Convention programs. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - N. C. A. A.: T. V. Arguments. (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - N. C. A. A./A. A. C. B. C.: Convention, Dallas. 1951 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - N. C. A. A.: Miscellaneous material. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Border Intercollegiate Athletic Conference, 1931-1961
    - Correspondence. 1931-1956 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Constitution and Eligibility Rules. 1932-1961 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous material. (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Minutes of meetings. 1931-1956 (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
    - 1st-25th Conferences. 1932-1959 (Box 20, Folder 6-8)
  - American Association of College Baseball Coaches, 1945-1967
    - A. A. C. B. C.: Membership lists. 1946-1961 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - A. A. C. B. C.: Meetings and minutes. 1946-1954, 1959-1967 (Box 21, Folder 2-3)
    - A. A. C. B. C.: Constitution and history. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - A. A. C. B. C.: All-star Game, Boston. 1946 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - A. A. C. B. C.: Miscellaneous material. (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Baseball Correspondence. 1945-1967 (Box 21, Folder 7-9)
- Series V: Supplemental Materials, 1899-1967
  - Major League Baseball Players. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - "Pros." (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Beginnings of Baseball. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Roster of Baseball Coaches (compiled by James F. McKale). 1957-1966 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - College All-American Baseball Teams. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - "The Most Famous Fifty." (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Baseball Clippings (miscellaneous). (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Baseball Material. (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - High School Baseball Tournaments and Track Meets. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - History of High School Basketball Tournaments. (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Basketball Tournaments. 1927-1958 (Box 23, Folder 3-5)
  - Coaching School, Flagstaff (programs of Arizona High School All-star Football Games). 1949-1959 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Falk Engineered Sport Facts. (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Photographs and Cartoons. (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Abe Chanin's series, "They Fought Like Wildcats," Arizona Daily Star (also original drawings). April 1954 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: "A 47-Year Career is Closed," by Arnott Duncan (McKale retirement), Arizona Days and Ways. May 19, 1957 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: "James Fritz McKale... Even Tempe Appreciates Him," (McKale retirement), Bisbee Daily Review. March 10, 1957 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Homecoming Edition, '56, Tucson Daily Citizen. 1956 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Photo of McKale installation in Arizona Sports Hall of Fame, Arizona Republic. February 4, 1959 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Stadium Section, p. 5-8, Arizona Wildcat. December 13, 1927 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Football clippings from Sam Mansfeld, Los Angeles Times. December 26, 1901, January 2, 1902 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings: Football clippings from Sam Mansfeld, Los Angeles Examiner. October 25, 1925 (Box 24)
  - Chart of University of Arizona Football Scores. 1899-1947 (Box 24)
  - Certificates and Awards (Helms Athletic Foundation Hall of Fame, Draft Board, Masonic, etc.). (Box 24)
  - National College Baseball Series, Omaha (clippings). 1950-1967 (Box 24)
  - 1932 Olympics, Los Angeles (clippings and programs). 1932 (Box 24)
- Series VI: Scrapbooks, 1914-1967
  - Scrapbooks. 1914-1921 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbooks. 1921-1928 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbooks. 1928-1937 (Volume 3)
  - Scrapbooks. 1937-1946 (Volume 4)
  - Scrapbooks. 1946-1951 (Volume 5)
  - Scrapbooks. 1951-1954 (Volume 6)
  - Scrapbooks. 1954-1958 (Volume 7)
  - Scrapbooks. 1958-1963 (Volume 8)
  - Scrapbooks. 1964-1967 (Volume 9)